[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, I was thinking about faith that's encouraged to be developed in this training.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a... one should train in developing faith, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it comes in that context of five powers, you know, faith, moral shame, moral dread, energy,
[SPEAKER_01]: And wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Five powers.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it is, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And faith in... Like, it's really, we all have faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have faith in the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, through reasoning, it's a good teaching, it makes sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you decide to walk the path.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because everyone has faith in some form or another.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, in regard to something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Faith in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Faith in education, faith in the family.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you think that... you believe in pham, you believe in sensuality, you say.
[SPEAKER_01]: You think it's gonna do you good, so you place your faith in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But somehow, you don't really recognize that we're placing faith in these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, a person who doesn't develop self-awareness on account of their own faith, which is... the faith is inevitable.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to have faith in something or believe in something.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you say, I don't believe in anything, that's your belief, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: But whether a person recognizes that or not...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now, if you recognize that... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is the...
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, then you start feeling responsibility for your faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, you can't be just justified, well, this is my belief.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you realize you choose to hold that belief.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're responsible, which means you can also choose to stop holding it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then you start to scrutinize your own beliefs.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you might actually arrive at a better belief and better truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, more honest, more wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's the power of faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the power of faith would be, say, somebody has fully scrutinized it, is fully accepted responsibility for it, and then he realizes what matters.
[SPEAKER_00]: Freedom from suffering matters.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's pretty much your... Whatever people do in their life, it's because of how they feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you realize, why don't I have faith, then, in something that actually pertains to this, like, absolute, fundamental, most crucial points of human existence?
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like a random faith in this or that, which is sort of perishable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in that sense, that faith becomes his power, because, because of that faith, he then starts to apply himself according to that instruction or teaching and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: The similarly, the, the, like, the, the, the, the faith in a doctor you would have.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unless you start scrutinizing, you're just going to put your faith in the first quack that comes from... comes your way, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh... you just won't... won't think further, because it's just, ah, well, you know, it's a doctor.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't need to know these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: He'll help me.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, he might want to help you, but he might not be able to.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, he himself is unaware that he's not actually adequate doctor.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, unless you start scrutinizing it as well, you're at a lot of risk.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you start scrutinizing, and then you place that faith correctly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Somebody is like, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: This guy can cure me from this, to this, to this.
[SPEAKER_00]: He can manage this symptom, or that symptom, or some other symptom.
[SPEAKER_00]: But this doctor uproots the actual illness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or so it seems.
[SPEAKER_00]: I need to find out.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in that sense, you develop faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that faith is a power, if it's placed rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because without that faith, you wouldn't have started practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's the same, like I said, like an Ārya... Ārya Saukha, the noble disciple, if he lacks faith, as in, could use a bit more faith in certain... certain aspects, that's why he's not free from sensuality yet.
[SPEAKER_00]: But by developing faith, as in just reminding himself that he just needs to stick to the principle, and even the sensuality will fade.
[SPEAKER_00]: The distraction of senses will go away.
[SPEAKER_00]: But by not having that faith, by not reminding yourself of just sticking to the principles, eh... those things still linger.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is... with lack of faith, a person will disrobe... a monk will disrobe... lack of faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: And some... some stay monks...
[SPEAKER_01]: They have faith, but they live their life with tears in their eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no result.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, they have faith in wholesome qualities.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, there's no result.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they see.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: They say, that's better.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still better than disrobing, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, even if the monk spends every single day of his life in tears of restraint and stuff, it's still better than disrobing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he's still actually making effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: That counts.
[SPEAKER_01]: But also, the faith is inevitable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what are you going to place your faith in?
[SPEAKER_01]: In something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either the world or the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or the renunciation world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Renunciation, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Beyond the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not really concerned with this particular faith or that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start looking at the fundamental aspects, and it exactly comes down to you either want the world, have faith in it, as something that's friendly, disposed towards you, or you don't have that faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have faith in actually renouncing the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't have it both ways.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't say, well, I'm renouncing the world, but I also think the world is quite... quite friendly towards me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Friendly disposition, safe place, all these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's either you accept it, or you want to overcome it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as we said, it's better to, even if, like, you're not necessarily arriving at any results, to still maintain the faith in renunciation, faith in overcoming the world, faith in saying no to the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there is a chance that wisdom can arise out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But certainly, wisdom won't arise if you said yes to the world and went back to the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because then it's difficult.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's through reasoning you have faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, if there's no results... Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then... Well, that's why monks disrobe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, mind you, many of them disrobe because they never really clarify the reasons for the practice to begin with.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, just... while the inspiration lasted... And that's another thing, actually.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's good to point out.
[SPEAKER_00]: People confuse faith and inspiration as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: They think when they feel inspired, they have faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has nothing to do with faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: Faith is that recognition of, this will be beneficial for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know for sure, but it seems so.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, because of that recognition, you apply yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly what the Buddha points out when he says, even if it hurts, even if there are no results, you keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it comes out of a recognition of wholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: But inspiration, inspiration, it's like when you're riding the wave.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, everything is easy because you're so inspired.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like a spiritual honeymoon.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that will have to run out.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you would have been better off not even giving rise to it, but some people can't help it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But once it runs its course, that's where the practice starts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like when you feel like doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's when you don't want to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you want to go back to the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, faith... Inspiration would be intoxication, a form of intoxication of your faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, there is a prospect of escape, freedom from suffering, so you get so inspired.
[SPEAKER_00]: In itself, that's not a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if that becomes your
[SPEAKER_00]: Main kind of... where your efforts are rooted in, then you will be in danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that intoxication will fail.
[SPEAKER_00]: That energy that you got from that initial inspiration will have to subside.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if that was the sole ground for your efforts, then your efforts will go with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's where the reflexive reasoning beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Actually, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: I might be inspired or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I'm inspired, great.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I'm not, well, that's also great.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is to keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not the...
[SPEAKER_01]: The thing with this faith power, it arises, it seems to suggest, with the other four powers.
[SPEAKER_01]: It seems to indicate what... those other four things indicate what the faith is about.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has already got wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's already consisting of energy.
[SPEAKER_00]: It contains, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It contains the possibility of it, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if your faith is just based on, I don't know, the appearance of somebody who's talking about some teaching or something,
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, or the charisma, or the, the energy, in verse comma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Man, that, that's not faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just intoxication.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's laziness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where you don't want to do the work of scrutinizing, but you just want to ride off the whale and spray, oh, he must be an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's go and live with him, as if that does anything to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only way you'll benefit from an arahant is if you start understanding what being an arahant is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, and also, how can Bhutujana know who an arahant is?
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you know it must be an arahant?
[SPEAKER_00]: What difference does it make?
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if your faith is not rooted in that blind intoxication, then you'll be scrutinizing.
[SPEAKER_00]: How does that person live?
[SPEAKER_00]: What do they teach?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do they live what they teach?
[SPEAKER_00]: Does their teaching make sense?
[SPEAKER_00]: Does their teaching pertain to the ultimate goal that results in liberation?
[SPEAKER_00]: If you start seeing yes, or if you're not sure, okay, come closer, have a closer look, ask more questions to yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, if it seems more right than other things you've encountered, then you have to start doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't just keep your distance and expect to understand it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where the faith comes in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once you scrutinize, okay, now, I'll start with this, then we'll see.
[SPEAKER_00]: You still don't commit to it blindly, you keep reflecting on what you're doing, but you stop looking for faults as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you start thinking like that from the start, then, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: If that was... if your efforts are correct, if your scrutinizing has reached a sufficient amount, you will start recognizing certain criteria, and then the wisdom will be arising from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the energy will be arising from wisdom, the whole, like... well, the verification from fear, from suffering will be arising from wisdom, from understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can build up a momentum from that, eh... Yeah, in a way, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not a momentum of inspiration, as in...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, it's obvious how I'm using inspiration.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, if other people use word inspiration for that manner, that's fine, but I, I, I qualify it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Five minutes ago, it's usually inspiration means, you know, it's kind of taking you, not you taking it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, faith, the inspiration takes, takes you, you don't, but faith you take it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Inspiration is when faith... when you make the faith take you, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Guru says you must have faith in wholesome qualities.
[SPEAKER_01]: He has faith in wholesome qualities.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he read these are wholesome, why they're wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's exactly the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like somebody who starts, they don't know why is wholesome wholesome and why is unwholesome unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they need to have faith in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you take on the virtue and the sīla.
[SPEAKER_00]: On trust.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have faith because, on some level, it's kind of making a bit of sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: That restraint is better than non-restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: And because of that faith, because of adhering to that principle that you just turn through the faith, then, then actually you get to see for yourself wholesome is wholesome, unwholesome is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when Sotāpanna's faith... sorry, when Pratyekabuddha becomes Sotāpanna, his previous faith becomes confirmed confidence in the dhamma, in the wholesome as wholesome, in that criteria.
[SPEAKER_00]: He sees it for himself now.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, for him, faith becomes inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: That faith is gone, because now he's confident about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: A degree of ignorance, as in you don't know it to the extent you don't know it, to that extent you have faith in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But not like faith, as I said, oh, I have faith that this will sort all my problems out.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I have faith that if I do this, I will sort all my problems out.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's a, like a, not even so subtle shift, but many people would sort of fail to, eh... Like faith in a meditation technique, for example.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, people can invest lots of effort and stuff, but the faith is placed on the content of what they're doing, as in, if I keep doing this, then the solution of all the problems, as in the enlightenment, freedom from suffering, will happen to me, because I've been adhering to this.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's completely blind faith, because they're completely divorced from any rational recognition of, well, wait a minute, what is...
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is it wholesome to just be doing this meditation technique?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I understanding anything?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: What are you going after when you're doing a random observance?
[SPEAKER_00]: You're going after experiences.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have faith that random experiences, one of them will be the right experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have faith that a random experience will do the work for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, will result in enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Adhering to wholesome
[SPEAKER_00]: Avoiding unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Reflecting upon wholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Reflecting upon unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Keeping the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having a sense of shame.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having a sense of shame.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there is no technique that can... Making an effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...that can encompass it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Making an effort, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: No one... no technique will make the effort for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: No technique will give you the wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: No technique will make you have a sense of shame.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or fear... People think, well, all these things are necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, the technique will get you to that point.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the faith in the point, that's the blind faith I talk about.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a mistaken faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: The faith should be in your effort, not to the point that randomly arises, sometimes does, sometimes doesn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some novelty experience, that is completely secondary.
[SPEAKER_00]: The faith is in that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Abandon... Has faith in abandoning unwholesome?
[SPEAKER_00]: Has faith in cultivating wholesome?
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you cultivate something or abandon something if you're not discerning what that thing is?
[SPEAKER_00]: And how can you discern it if you never make the effort to think about it?
[SPEAKER_00]: If all of your efforts are aimed at suppressing your thinking and focusing on one point and whatnot, to get the energy releases and so on, and then I'll see I had faith and I had this energy release, I must be a sūtra.
[SPEAKER_00]: All those things occur bodily, in the body, for you, and have nothing to do with understanding the nature of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you should have faith in...
[SPEAKER_00]: I have faith in the possibility of understanding the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not that I'm going to have faith in this particular method of walking or breathing or something, whereby I won't have to think about anything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I just adhere to it, it will sort me out.
[SPEAKER_01]: While not in the Buddha's teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, having faith in the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: His own effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: He didn't follow so-and-so's technique, which bing, bing, and then all of a sudden led him to enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when they asked him how, he described the understanding of the suffering and fear from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He didn't say, oh, well, by walking three steps to the left, four steps to the right, by watching your nostrils and observing the movements of your belly, or sensations in your shoulders and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, by understanding suffering, cause of suffering,
[SPEAKER_00]: cessation of suffering and the way it leads to the cessation of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: A full understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: A full understanding is exactly that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You understood it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, like, knowingly, for him, knowingly, those things arose, knowingly, knowingly, knowingly, those things ceased.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, he knew, he understood it through and through.
[SPEAKER_00]: It wasn't like, oh, this is wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, it must be this experience of freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means there's no understanding there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was just a guesswork.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just mystifying now, and hoping that it's that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the fact that you don't know that it is, means it isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because freedom from suffering comes through the knowledge of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He knows that he knows, as the Buddha would describe, sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: He knows that he knows freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just he had experience and then he kind of deduced that he must be understanding freedom from suffering because, you know, I suffer less.
[SPEAKER_00]: Suffering less doesn't mean you're free from the nature of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Suffer less means that you suffer less due to circumstances or whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means then, you're gonna suffer more.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you think that suffering less matters, as a measure,
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, you suffer less amount, but it's still the suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, all the deva realms, all the deva realms... That, and also, if you have that view, means, you're not going to make the work, make the effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: The, eh... No, I was going to say, if that's the view, means, and if you think that, oh, I suffer less, thus, it's good, my practice is bearing fruit.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't see any other distinction of full understanding, but I suffer less.
[SPEAKER_00]: And fail to see that it's because of circumstances, because of the restraint and so on, not because of wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when circumstances change, and they will, when the suffering hits you back, it's going to be too late to do anything about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, if you suffer less on account of your restraint and faith in the practice, that's great.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that in itself, it's not a solution.
[SPEAKER_00]: Suffering still touches you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to be not touched by the suffering in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you can say you truly... not... you're not free from suffering just circumstantially, but through the understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, if... if... if freedom from suffering is measure of... of your understanding, then, exactly, many Putugeno would sort of think... well, you... you could argue then that... then they're fine, as Putugenos, because they don't really suffer much.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: How much you're exposed to suffering on a particular basis, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: What matters is, as the Buddha said, whether you're prey to suffering, as in whether you're liable to suffering to affect you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is a possibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: I might not suffer now, but is this true for the future?
[SPEAKER_00]: If something happens to me, something unforeseen, an accident, will I be unaffected by it?
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you're not sure, means you do not
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you can truly say, yeah, it's not a problem for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you will know that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you think about, think about an accident happening to you in the future, and see, even that thought is actually contains the displeasure of that prospect, that possibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you're not free from suffering, that thought will already be affecting you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you are, it won't be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you know, whatever comes through that thought, won't affect you either.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going to be an extreme inconvenience.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can disable it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, you won't suffer on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, so, yeah, if I lose all my... all my things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fire, flood, thieves, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Will I be affected if all this disappears?
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't have to go and start throwing your things away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just dwell on that thought, the prospect of it being taken away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is there emotional resistance to it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is there, like, a bit anxious or something, the prospect of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's your work.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, not throwing away things, or accumulating, for that matter, but actually undoing that emotional connection to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that thing is not undone because you don't think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is its fuel.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not thinking about that emotional assumption, connection, craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you're feeding it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you think about it, you stop feeding it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why there's all that persistent energy, all the way, all the time, constantly, until you're in arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't have to... Because then the energy becomes your mode of being.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your mindfulness becomes your mode of being.
[SPEAKER_00]: And energy, effort, mindfulness becomes effortless.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Faith, faith, as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Structures, faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: In a way, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, that faith gets fully, fully converted into confidence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Faith and confidence.
[SPEAKER_00]: You verified what you had faith in.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through verifying it, you don't have faith that this works, because now you know that it works.
[SPEAKER_00]: Trust, confidence.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, faith, the right faith, it's like borrowing wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Borrowing the knowledge that you arrive at.
[SPEAKER_00]: Borrowing it beforehand as something to guide you in that direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you arrive at it, and that's how you pay it back.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: But exactly what you said, if that faith is not rooted in that wisdom, you won't be borrowing wisdom when you when you develop faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're borrowing more ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no reason to relax in the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no reason, there's no need.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only time you need to relax in your practice is when you assume that pleasures of your senses is relaxation.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when people want to relax or distract from the practice, because they still assume that absence of effort means relaxation.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it doesn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wholesome things means relaxation.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you don't know that, then the pleasure and kind of unwholesome is what relaxation is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Distraction through sight, sound, smell, taste, touches.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pleasure through sight, sound, smell, taste, touches.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you recognize that, no, that's not... that also requires effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the truly relaxing thing is the thing that is effortless, the thing that is free, the thing that doesn't require maintenance, the thing that doesn't require management, the thing that doesn't require fueling.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's not upādāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Upādāna is the fuel that requires the fueling.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, renunciation is a true relaxation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Saying no to sensuality is a true way of relaxing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But not for the one who still has the view that pertains to sensuality, that values sensuality, that doesn't see the danger in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, saying no to sensuality would mean, like, saying no to the pleasure of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And pleasure, for me, means relaxation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, I am saying no to relaxation.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if you have faith in renunciation, and remove your faith in the pleasure of senses, which is what you think relaxation is, you will come to see that, yeah, you were mistaken.
[SPEAKER_00]: The true effortless thing is renunciation.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a negative.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not about doing this or that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about not doing this or that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's effortless.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's a freedom from unwholesome states, unwholesome qualities.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's effortless.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: It requires knowledge of those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the...
[SPEAKER_00]: Initial discernment, they can kind of allow you to... to get a sense of the direction of the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you just stick with, I have faith in this or that, but you don't scrutinize it further, you don't reflect upon it further, well, then itself won't take you anywhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: And without faith, you wouldn't... you wouldn't be able to interchange... well, cultivate jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, sure, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't get closer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you wouldn't know where to look.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: The right faith, it's like borrowing of that which you want to achieve.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course, it can be very generic, inaccurate, just borrowing something without much, without concentrated substance in it, substance that you need.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if you scrutinize it, clarify it further, then your faith becomes more accurate as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, your faith actually pertains, in a more concentrated manner, to that which you're trying to achieve.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you scrutinized it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where the sadhana-sādhi, the one who kind of puts the faith first, has the weakest of the faculties.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he just, he just takes the faith, and does what he discerned through that faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which, in scope, it's much...
[SPEAKER_00]: More limited than for somebody who actually discerns even the faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he puts the discernment factor first, the dhammanusārī.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course, dhammanusārī will carry his own faith through his discernment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sādhanusārī will be developing his discernment through his own faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, if he put faith first and leave it first, it's much slower and more riskier today.
[SPEAKER_00]: You could get away with that back in the day, when there were lots of arahants around you, teaching and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But today, it's more like the other way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Also, stuff you hear has nothing to do with the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to first make the effort to undo all of the wrong notions of what you think dhamma is, and then start practicing right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't afford to just run off faith, because sooner or later you're going to learn that something's completely wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you won't see it, because you don't have a reference point at that stage.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, putting discernment first, it's much more unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: More anxiety, more dread, more doubt, more pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, what's the big deal?
[SPEAKER_00]: You suffered millions of lifetimes, you will suffer millions of lifetimes.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is one lifetime more?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because at least you're trying to practice dhamma, right?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, even if you suffer, as the Buddha said, even if you spend the rest of your life in tears of restraint and don't get anywhere, it still worth something.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still better, because you never do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: For years and years,
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't... if you can't figure it all out, it was confusing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Faith in cultivating wholesome qualities.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Faith in... Come back to the fundamentals.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's easy to understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's why we've been speaking in such a... like a... well, in a fundamental manner.
[SPEAKER_00]: It wouldn't be particular.
[SPEAKER_00]: We have faith in this or that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Faith in recognition of wholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, if I stick to this, it can only result in good, which is why it's wholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't see it directly, but I have a good faith that it is so.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and the same by body and speech and the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not just...
[SPEAKER_00]: You abstain from killing and lying and so on, but you also abstain from unwholesome speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, gossip, careless chatter, all these things are unwholesome from their point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you abstain from that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You abstain from malicious speech, false speech, divisive speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you go further.
[SPEAKER_00]: You abstain from thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you know you're not going to say anything or do anything, but you stop entertaining thoughts as well, of such nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the method.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the meditation technique you should be developing.